[Music]
Stanford
University all right we started to
explore
entanglement I had actually started to
think about doing Bells theorems uh
tonight but
um I decided not to do it
yet it's a complicated story Bell's
theorem and it's very
lovely but more important than the
theorem itself is what it says and so I
want it uh I want to get as much as
possible tonight to what it
says and what entanglement
um has to tell us about the nature of
systems sometimes people say the nature
of reality I don't like the word reality
I think it uh it's
misleading okay um
in looking on the
internet at the the messages you guys
send back and forth they're very
interesting and and many of them have
some very interesting points in them
there's a terminology which I would
discourage at least un unless you know
what it means uh with greater precision
and I've seen this all over the place
people say entanglement is share when
two Quantum systems share the same share
a state I've never understood what that
means to share a
state um Quantum systems have States if
they're composite Quantum systems they
have States uh you can say that a
Quantum system a pair of quantum systems
when they make a given Quantum system
share a state if you like but it just
means the state of the composite system
um the important idea about
entanglement is not so much that systems
share a state that they always do it's
the important thing is that they are not
described by a product State a product
State being a state in which the wave
function of the system and we'll talk
about wave have we talked about wave
functions very much I don't think we
have let's begin by talking about wave
functions and then I want to move on to
the concept of a density Matrix
this will make it much easier for us to
think about
entanglement first of all the notion of
a wave
function a wave
function may or may not have anything to
do with
waves the
concept grew historically out of the
quantum mechanics of particles and the
relation and the probability description
of them in terms of
waves but the uh the
logical concept of a wave function is
one that you can apply to any Quantum
system and in general it doesn't have to
do with wave motion of any particular
kind the basic idea of a wave function
is the
following you have a Quantum State let's
call the quantum
State ah
capital P I'll use the letter capital P
to denote a a generic Quantum state of a
system I think previously I've been
using A's and B's but I'm going to start
using
SII uh as a generic Quantum state for
pretty much any system and also I have a
basis system the basis system is
typically labeled by a collection of
igen values of
something uh it might be labeled by one
or more
variables if there are several commuting
operators in a system you can specify
simultaneously the igen values of more
than one thing and in many cases you
want to do that and the basis vectors in
those cases are labeled by a collection
of observables or a collection of igen
values of perhaps several quantities
I'll give you an example um if you're
talking about the motion of a
particle then the X and Y and Z
coordinates of the particle are
commuting variables the things that
don't commute are the components of
momentum with the components of position
I know we haven't done this yet but
uh the other hand the three components
of position all commute with each other
that means they can be specified simult
mously a useful basis for studying the
quantum mechanics of a particle is a
basis which is labeled by the three
coordinates of the particle I'll wait
for
uh yeah I'll give her a
hand all right so we have a basis and
the basis is labeled by a collection of
I
values let's label them let's don't have
a decent pen all right A B C however
many uh commuting variables there are
that need to be specified in order
to specify a
system and the inner
product of the basis Vector with the
state of the system itself is called the
wave function and in fact we can write
that s since these objects here form a
basis we can
say that this is a sum I still don't
have a decent
pin ah a little bit better a sum over
the basis vectors which means a sum over
this collection of igen values a dot dot
dot of the inner
product of the basis
vectors with the state
Vector times the basis
vectors we've written this equation this
kind of equation down before what it
says is that the expansion coefficients
that you use to expand the vector in
basis vectors are just the inner
products of the vector with the basis
vectors this object is called the wave
function right
here and it's a function of the A's B's
and
C's so let's give it a name let's call
it little
s of a b c and so
forth It's called the wave
function and it's defined in such a way
that the state Vector s is equal to the
sum over a over
all the indices which it takes to
specify the basis
times s of a b and c and so forth s of a
b and c of the coordinates of the um not
the coordinates
the an example if we're just talking
about a single spin
then a complete set of commuting
variables necessary to specify uh a
vector is for example just Sigma Z the Z
component of Spin and then s would just
be the probability amplitudes for the
spin to be up or the spin to be down be
a function of one variable that variable
would take on the values up and down if
we had two
spins then we would label a basis of
vectors with ups for once ups and downs
for one spin ups and downs for the other
Spin and it would take two labels to
label a state Vector not just one the
two labels would be the labels of the
two spins and that's all that that's all
we're talking about here might take
multiple labels to label a spin to label
basis
vector and if so just display them here
and then by definition as pure
definition the wave function of the
system you can think of it two ways you
can think of it as the set of um
coefficients the set of coefficients
that you use to expand an arbitrary
Vector in terms of the basis vectors or
you can think of them as the inner
products the inner
products of the state Vector with the
basis vectors themselves that is called
the wave function and shring is wave
function is a special case of it which
we will not get to at the
moment but it is a special case of
it question
okay so if you know the wave function of
a system you know it State vector and
you can compute all sorts of things you
can compute
um
uh expectation values and all sorts of
things yeah this looks a little like a
for transform in some basis is a for
transform
y it is a for transform uh for the case
of position and momentum if
yes yeah uh so in that case you go back
and forth well no the fora transform is
going back and forth between different
basis
sets okay here I've chosen a particular
basis set supposing I wanted to use a
different basis instead of Sigma Z Sigma
X then I would have to transform these
wave functions function somehow they
look different in the X basis and that
that's the analog oforia
transform
okay now I want to introduce a concept
called the density Matrix if we have
just a single
system this is the way we think about
the state of the system oh let's talk
about expectation values let's talk
about expectation values supposing we
have some observable let's call it l ah
ah let's call it l it's some observable
and it has Matrix elements what do I
Matrix elements mean they
mean if this is a basis Vector I won't
bother writing out multiple labels let's
just put one label there to summarize
all the labels and another label over
here a
prime these are called The Matrix
elements of the
observable okay The Matrix elements of
the observable the observable acts on a
basis vector and then you project it
onto another basis vector and that's
called L I
suppose uh a prime
a just
notation okay now supposing I want to
calculate the expectation value of L in
a state whose wave function is s let's
see how we do that we take SII I'm going
to as I said I'm just going to restrict
myself to a single uh a single a here
but the same thing would hold if there
were multiple
A's all right so what do we do we take
the state Vector on the left the uh the
K Vector the K Vector maybe we should
write out the K Vector here sorry the
bra Vector the bra VOR this is the C
Vector the bra Vector is the sum over A
and B but you know I want to use
different indices here I want to call
them a prime and B Prime they're being
summed over so it doesn't matter what I
call them I just don't want to confuse
them with these and then we're going to
have uh bra vectors ABC
or times now do I put s here s
star so exactly the same kind of
expression for the bra Vector except
complex conjugated
coefficients good now let's calculate
s
l s that's the expectation value or the
average value of L in the quantum State
s and we do it just by plugging in the
left the left bra Vector here is the sum
I'm just a single index a prime a
prime s of a
prime that constructs the bra Vector the
head Vector I will have to write another
sum a sum of a a of s of
a time
a summing on a turns this into the C
Vector S capital S summing over a prime
turns this into the bra
Vector the corresponding bra vector and
in between we sandwich
L right now thiso somebody please
correct me what did I write
wrongar
siar all right we take the size and the
side stars out of the expression they're
just numbers and so the whole thing is a
sum of a prime and a sar of a prime s of
a times the inner product or the
sandwich a prime L A that's exactly The
Matrix element of L between a and a
prime so that's
L which one is it a prime a I
think and this reduces every um
expectation value to a calculation in
terms of wave functions a s always a s
and always a s
star times a matrix element of the
observable that we're interested in all
right so this is a basic
formula for the expectation value of
anything that we might be interested
in
okay basically all of quantum mechanics
is contained in there the expectation
value of everything in the world that's
uh that's just about everything we ever
may want to be interested
in and so let's put this equation over
here and keep it over
here now supposing we have a composite
system composed of two subsystems let's
call them alyses and Bob's
subsystems all right Alice has uh
control of one of them Bob has control
of the other uh and maybe even there are
times when uh when uh they don't have
control of them but uh we just call them
two subsystems alyses and bobs
then and in fact let's use a
now to represent a complete set of
observables for Alice's
subsystem everything that Alice needs to
know in order to specify a basis for her
subsystem and B are the set of variables
for Bob subsystem when we talked about
spin I think we called Alice's variable
too and Bob's variable Sigma if I
remember correctly but uh we just these
are a complete set of things complete
set of variables for Alice and this is a
complete set of variables for Bob
Alice's States for her subsystem would
look like this Bobs would look like that
maybe we want to use a different
notation so we don't uh wind up
confusing the two Vector spaces but then
there's the composite Vector space the
composite Vector space is the vector
space describing the composite system
and that has a basis which consists of
an A and the
B when a runs over all its values and B
runs over all its values we have a
complete basis of the combined
system okay so now let's talk about wave
functions of the composite
system again we have a state
Vector the State Vector s is a state
Vector in the composite in the tensor
product space the space made by
tensoring producting A's and B's
together it has as its basis vectors A
basis Vector from a and a basis Vector
from B and now I want to Define in the
same way the not the the notion of a
composite wave function so what is it
it's just the in product of s with the
basis
vectors and what is it a function of
it's now a function of two sets of
variables or two variables s of A and B
different B here this yeah okay here it
is it's a function of the variables of
the two subsystems it depends on two of
them okay so that's the wave function
now we have notion of a wave function of
a composite system and let's talk
about uh observables of a composite
system the observables of a composite
system first of all among those
variables are the ones which would
describe the separate subsystems by
themselves so let's suppose that
l and
m are two observables one of them having
to do with alysis subsystem
Alice and the other one having to do
with Bob
subsystem I could call them Els sub a
and Els subb but I won't I'll call them
L&M uh how do we
represent observables acting on the
composite space of states the answer is
simple The Operators associated with
Alice's subsystem
act on Alice's piece of the state vector
vector and leave Bob's piece of the
state Vector
unchanged that's what we did when we did
spins we said Bob's Sigma matrices acted
on his half of the wave function or his
half of the basis vectors and were
completely passive or Alice's piece of
the state Vector was completely passive
just was bypassed by by these operators
so what that
says what that says is that
Alice's
observables are
matrices they're
matrices that can be written as L
of
a prime B Prime just like L here has a
primed variable and an unprimed variable
but now the single index is replaced by
two indices and a and b what does this
correspond to this corresponds to the
sandwich
a prime B Prime
l
a whatever a whatever this stands for
but L only belongs to
Alice's space of states only belongs to
Alice's system so the question is what
then do we say about this Matrix here to
say to
indicate that it has no effect on Bob's
variables
answer is simple we make it
proportional to the identity Matrix in
Bob's
variables the identity operator the
identity operator in a uh in a space is
the operator whose Matrix elements are
The Chronic Delta symbol that's the
identity operator and the identity
operator on a subsystem does nothing to
that subsystem the identity operator
simply gives the same Vector back in
other words if you apply the identity
operator it does nothing but now what
we're doing is applying the identity
operator on Bob's half of the system but
the observable that's supposed to be
associated with Alice's half of the
subsystem is represented by the same
Matrix that she would have used had she
not even known about
Bob had she not even known about Bob she
would have used the Matrix a l a prime
and a to describe her
observable how does she describe it in
the bigger Hilbert space she says it
does nothing to Bob's variables and so
it's just the identity Matrix in Bob's
uh half of the
space that's Alice's variables we could
say the same thing about Bobs
M of a prime and B Prime and A and
B just equal to the chronica Delta of
Alice's variables times The Matrix that
Bob would have
used to
describe the subsystem had he not known
anything about
Alice
okay
let's
prove some things about uh about the
setup here first of all let's calculate
expectation value
of Alice's variables in a product State
a product state is one in which the two
systems are not entangled with each
other and let's see what we
get what would you expect to get if you
had an unentangled State describing
Alice's and Bob
subsystems and you consider the
expectation value of Alice's uh variable
you get exactly what you would have
gotten had Bob not been there altogether
so let's check that out what do I mean
first of all by a product uh State I
explained what a product state was but
now let me explain what a product state
is in the language of wave functions
it's very simple it means that the wave
function is a product of two wave
functions one for Alice and one for Bob
that's all it means a product a product
state is one whose wave function s of A
and
B Alice's and Bob's variables is just a
product so let's see how shall we denote
that let's call
it um well let's just call it s Alis of
a and fi
Bob of
B it factorizes it's a f a product of
two functions it's a function of two
variables but it's a product of two
functions each of one
variable it's pretty clear that if it
factorizes like this then Alice can
think of this as the wave function for
her subsystem and Bob thinks of this as
the wave function for his
subsystem okay let's calculate now
Alice's expectation value of L if this
happens to be the wave function so what
do we do we first take side we're going
to make a sandwich we going to make a
sandwich with a s star on one side a s
on the other side and L in between all
right so siar that's siar of Alice of
a a
prime uh F star Bob of B Prime this
is where do we write it
there
uh that's the complex conjugate of the
wave function as a a function of a prime
and B Prime what
next next we put in to the sandwich
L of a prime B Prime A and B it's a
matrix two one entry here one entry here
but it's simple it's just L of a prime
and
a Time Delta BB
Prime and then we close it up with the
other half of the sandwich which is this
up here S A of
a f b of B and we sum as always we sum
over everything in sight a prime a b
Prime
B that's the rule for calculating an
expectation value so what do we get
first of all the Delta BB Prime that
tells us to set B Prime equal to B so
let's do that first off let's do that
I'll just
erase so B Prime equal to B all right
I'm let you write down your notes if you
want so B Prime equal to B and remove
the chronica
Delta now B is equal to B Prime now
notice the only thing that depends on B
is f star B and 5
b what the sum over B Prime was done
when I set b equal to B Prime and now
there's a sum over B of f star five what
does that
give one under the assumption of course
that Bob's wave function is
normalized under the assumption that
Bob's half of the wave function is
normalized so that his total probability
for his all his measurements he could do
is one then sum over B of f star of B *
5 of B is just one and what do the whole
thing reduced to the whole thing reduces
to exactly what's up there we can remove
the
F take them
out put them down here that sum is just
one and the rest of it is just exactly
what's up on the top of the Blackboard
there in other words in a product State
the expectation value of any of Alice's
operators are exactly the same as
if Bob wasn't there and it doesn't
doesn't matter what Bob's wave function
is as long as it's a
product what about uh one of Bob's uh
expectation values what would happen if
we stuck stuck a bob operator in there
well then instead of The Chronic a Delta
of B's let's go back we have B and B
Prime B and B
Prime uh yeah B and B Prime B Prime over
here and instead of l a L we would have
M of B and B
Prime Delta a a prime and now we would
set a prime equal to
a sum that would again give us one and
we would get the same we get basically
the same thing that I wrote up
here
Bob except it would
be Bob's wave function f
star Bob
of B Prime M of B Prime
B times F Bob of B which is exactly what
Bob would have
done had he not known about Alice so
product states are really just that
there's States in which um one party
just doesn't know about the other
there's no correlation there's no no um
information in one of them about the
other
okay we can say a little bit more about
correlation let's suppose now that we
were
interested in the product of an ALICE
variable and a bob variable we're
interested in the expectation value of L
* m let's see what we get
expectation in in the product State
strictly product States for the moment
we go back up to
here and now instead of
writing MB is this BB Prime this should
be b b
Prime instead of Delta of a and a prime
if we're taking the product of l and m
then what do I put
here l
if I'm interested in the operator which
represents the
product of two variables one for Alice
and one for Bob instead of putting the
unit operator over here for for Alice I
will simply put
in Alice's
operator not M Alice
L now this just factorizes let's look at
all the a depend depence here's a
dependence here's a dependence here's a
dependence that factorizes that's
completely separate from the B
dependence I could take everything with
a B dependence and put it on one side
everything with an a dependence and put
it on the other side and do the A and B
summations
independently can you see that that uh
all right let's let's write it
out it's sum of a a prime a b Prime B of
s Alis
star of a prime l a a prime s Alis of
a all times five Bob
star of B Prime M of BB Prime and F of B
the sums can be done quite independently
we can put this sum over here same thing
I haven't changed it we're summing over
everything B's and A's and we see that
what we get is just the product we get
the product of the expectation value of
L times the expectation value of
m not surprising if we have a product
State and Alice does her measurement and
Bob does his measurement and we then
come together and compare the
measurements and ask what was the
product of the
measurements the expectation value will
just be the product the expectation
value of the product operator will be
the product of expectation values and we
can write this this way let's uh let's
write
it in a
form it says for for product States for
product what's called Product
States the expectation value of L and
times M now remember L belongs to Alice
M belongs to Bob and uh they operate in
different halves of the system the
expectation value of L * m is just the
expectation value of L times the
expectation value of
M now
is this something that we expect to
always be true for every
state that the expectation value in fact
even in classical probability theory if
we have a probability distribution for
two variables in general is it true that
the average of the product is the
product of the average only if variables
are independent which means what in
terms of the probability
distribution exactly what you written
there it means that it factorizes
it means that the probability
distribution is a product of two
probability distributions right well
what if what if it's not true what if
the probability distribution does not
factorize then this quantity here the
difference between the average of L * m
and the product of averages of l and m
is called the correlation between l and
m it's called a correlation
and it is a measure of how much these
variables are correlated we'll do we'll
we'll see some examples this is called a
correlation and whenever the
correlation Whenever there is anything
in the
system an ALICE variable and a bob
variable whose correlation is not
zero that's an indication of
entanglement if you can find any pair of
variables one of Alice's and one of
Bob's
such that the average of the product is
not the product of the averages then
you're experiencing
entanglement
um I think we did an example last
time we took what I called the singlet
state which was up down down minus down
up over theare < TK of
two this is p and this is not a product
State and in this state we took the
expectation value of Bob's variable
Sigma
[Music]
Z we took the expectation value of
Alice's variable which I think was t z
do you remember what these were what's
what's the average value of uh Bob's
variable let's say the first entrance
here the first entry stands for Bob
here's
Bob Bob here's
Alice what would you guess in this state
the average of Sigma Z
is not the state but the combined
State no zero why is it zero because it
has as much probability of being up as
being
down has probability one has probability
1/2 to be up and one half to be down so
the average of Bob's variable is zero I
think we worked that out last
time what about Alice's
variable it's also up as much as it's
down okay it's also expectation value
zero what about all right so first
step both of these are zero in this
case what about the product what about
the product of Sigma Z and t z what's
its average
value well we worked it out last
time we got an answer anybody remember
the answer minus one minus one but you
can just look at this thing and you can
say in both vectors here the spins are
opposite so in either case here the
product of the spins is minus one it's
pretty clear that this whole thing is an
igen Vector of the product because on
either Vector here the product is minus
one act with Sigma
Z act with Sigma Z you'll get you know
what will happen
so it'll just change sign so yes this
has the product of the sigma Z is equal
to one minus one excuse me
so they're entangled in fact in this
case they're what I'll call maximally
entangled they're very
entangled uh if you can find any pair of
variables which are correlated in this
form the quantum state is entangled do
you remember now here it's completely
obvious that the average of Sigma Z is
zero for just the reasons that I said uh
Sigma Z and to Z up appears as much as
down for Bob and down appears as much as
up for Alice and so it's clear the
average is zero what about the average
of Sigma X do you
remember it's zero but that's not
obvious is
it that's not
obvious but we did it last time go back
to your notes and you'll discover that
not only is the expectation value of
Sigma z0
but Sigma X is also equal to zero the
average on the other hand you'll also
find that the product of Bob Sigma X and
Alice's to X is again equal to
minus1
so the sigma Z's and the to z's are
correlated the sigma x's and the to X's
are correlated and what about y same
thing same exact thing you can work that
out we know what these operators do you
can apply them to the states and
calculate what their expectation value
is so this state is a highly highly
entangled or a highly correlated State
being correlated and being entangled of
basically the same
idea question yeah uh in the general
case if you flip the L and the M's
around to each other
is you know flip the L's and the M's
lmus bracket L equals m
lus is
that I'm saying no they just flip the
L's in the N oh yeah that's equal
right all
right there's a point there which I may
not have mentioned all operators
associated with one system commute with
all operators associated with the other
system so it doesn't matter in which
order you write
them that's independent of whether the
system is entangled
doesn't matter which order you are
you're right then excuse me yeah um I
guess I'm missing something um when you
wrote that down you showed us that you
have a product state of where L is a
state in Alice's and yeah then this is
equal to zero that's equal to zero mhm
yeah what does lm mean that it's I mean
You' got it written up there isn't that
doesn't that a product State this no
what in the state is these are the
states these are the observables right
right doesn't that l m mean a product
State l no L's and M's are not
States yeah there are size in
here this is a statement about the uh
the state
vectors
right okay one other point is worth just
noticing when I say things are
correlated that the spins are correlated
I mean it what I mean is that you can
learn something about one variable by
looking at the other if you know that
this is the state if you happen to know
that this is the state then if you know
Bob's if you measure Bob's
variable and you find out that it's up
then in that component of the state
which is the only one that's left after
you measure Bob Alice is down in a
product product State you learn nothing
about one system by measuring anything
about the other in a highly entangled
State you learn a great deal about one
system by measuring the other
one okay that's what entanglement means
on the other hand it may also follow and
it may also be true that in a highly
entangled State beforehand if you happen
to know the state you may know very
little about each individual
piece for example in the singlet State
here there is what is the what is the
probability that Bob's variable is up
1/2 what is the probability that Bob's
variable is down
1/2 so in this state
knowing knowing everything about this
state you still know nothing about
whether Bob measures up or down if he
does a
measurement curious you know nothing at
all about whether Bob measures up or
down you know nothing at all about
whether Alice measures up or down but
you know everything about the product of
them that if Bob does his measurement
Alice does her measurement and you
compare them afterwards every single
time if this is the state that you put
the system into the product will be
minus so this is an example of this odd
thing in quantum mechanics that you can
know everything about a composite system
and know nothing about the
pieces that's what this is telling you
you know everything or when I say you
know everything I mean you know as much
as quantum mechanics allows you to know
this is the state of the system you're
not going to do any better than that
that's all there is to know about
it what you know about it is that Sigma
time tow whether it be Sigma X or to X
how this is true for the X Y or Z
component separ L that the product of
Alice's variable and Bob's variable is
minus one that's a lot to know but it's
not as much as you would know
classically classically if you knew
everything about a system you would know
everything about the
constituents as well as things that you
could measure about them that you could
combine together in quantum mechanics
you can't know you either you can say
you can't know everything or to the
extent that everything is everything you
can know in this case you you know
everything about the combined system and
you know nothing about its
constituents that's the really odd thing
about
entanglement that's the extremely odd
property of in of quantum mechanics that
allows uh such
nonsense wouldn't that just mean you
can't separate decompose the system
without destroying information yeah yeah
yeah it it it does mean
that when you write
LM uh I'm a little confused is
that
uh measure M and then measure l no no no
it's the product of L and all right
let's let's be very clear be very clear
the
operation the operation mathematical
operation of multiplying a state vector
by an operator is not got anything to do
with the actual physical act of
measuring it I know but the syntax looks
the
same
the the I'm not sure the syntax is not
the same the syn I'm not sure what
syntax means I assume it means the words
it just means how do I interpret l m on
the board that's
all the product of The Operators yes yes
it means you act first with them and
then L okay yeah yeah it but it doesn't
mean that you've measured them it means
this is just a
mathematical thing
right it's the same is true in the
classical mechanics I can multiply the
momentum of something by the position of
something else that doesn't mean I
measure measured them just because I
multiplied the the the two things
together physical active measurement uh
it's not the operators which act on on
the states it's the detectors or
apparatuses which act on the
system so in words when you do a
measurement a detector or an apparatus
acts on the system and gives a
result the in the space of states
a operator acts on a
vector not a detector acting on a system
quite different
concepts yeah before we make a
measurement on on an electron um unless
we already know how it's been prepared
which is a special case where in that
case we can describe the state as linear
combination BAS but before we uh make a
measurement we might know nothing about
it we might know a little bit about it
but no matter how much we know will have
to be expressed in terms of
probabilities not in terms of the
vectors yes um so in the case where
there's a correlation uh between two
electrons and let's say it's not a pure
correlation it's it's a a part it's not
a product it's not a product and it's
not a purely inted State it's somewhere
between it's not a what a a sign state
for example it's a somewhat inang State
exactly so if then after we made the
sigma measurement and we we want to
describe the tow electron we would still
have to describe to in terms of
probabilities we wouldn't be able to
specify in terms of of uh a combination
okay I'm not exactly sure what you're
getting at but maybe this will
help
um if we have the quantum state of a
single spin let's suppose somebody told
us what the St the quantum state of a
spin
was all right then for any Quantum State
there is always an observable in
particular some component of Sigma which
is definite which is
predictable every P that's obvious for
the states um up and down it's obvious
for the States left and right for the
state up if you measure Sigma Z it's
definite if you
measure if you know that the state is
right and you measure Sigma X it's
definite this is more General given any
Quantum State whatever of a spin there
exists a direction this you can prove
that exists a direction for which the
spin is definite okay curiously when you
combine the system together into an
entangled State like this there is no
direction in which the spin is definite
in fact there is no Direction Sigma X
Sig for one of the spins each one of the
spins either alyses or Bob's has average
value zero in every
direction no matter what direction you
pick x y z or anything in between the
average of the spin of Bob spin in this
state is
zero so and here's a Quantum state in
which Bob can say nothing what he can
know the quantum State fully and as I
said has equal probability for up and
down in every
direction um I'm not sure if that's what
you are addressing or
not my question in a nutshell is if if
we have a partial correlation oh partial
okay correlation is somewhere between
zero and and one all right so we put we
put a big number here and a small number
here yeah so we we've measured one and
and then the other could be expressed as
various probabilities of Sigma X and
sigma y yes yes yes yes we can calculate
all the probabilities just calculate
them yeah um okay could you remind us
the
physical for single state say it again
what is what would be an example of a
physical experiment corresponding to a
single state good
good good that's that's an important
obviously an important question uh
another way to ask you is how would you
prepare a state a system in the singlet
State all right um all right I'll tell
you something about the singlet State
the singlet state has the property that
it's an igen Vector of a certain
operator it's IG Vector of many
operators but in particular it's an igen
Vector of Sigma X tox you can prove it
it's it's actually an igen Vector of
Sigma X tox it's an igen Vector of Sigma
y
toy and it's an igen vector of Sigma Z
to Z what's the igen value for each one
of these minus one and the igen value is
the same for all of them that means that
it's an igen Vector of any linear any
combination of these with igen value
minus one any one of them acts on the
singlet State gives back minus the
singlet State any combination of them
will give back minus the singlet state
so in particular if I take this object
here the singlet state is also an igen
Vector of
this now this is a funny
thing Alice and Bob can't easily measure
this whole quantity here why because
Alice can't measure tox and to Y
simultaneously by separate measurements
this would be hard to measure can't be
measured by separate
measurements uh why because no separate
no separate measurement can measure to X
and to Y at the same time or to Z at the
same time but this object is a perfectly
good Herm Mission operator and there
must exist a way of measuring it but
more to the point right now there's a
way of preparing a state which is an
igen Vector of this now what state the
singlet State the singlet state is an
igen Vector of this object with IG value
minus three it's an igen value of this
one with minus one this one with minus
one and this one with minus one the
whole thing has igen value minus three
it's a but point is the igen vectors of
this product or the sum of products here
include the uh the singlet State there's
a particular one you can also write this
as just sigma.
to Sigma X tox Sigma y toy Sigma Z to Z
that if these were ordinary classical
vectors you would write it as sigma. to
now if you take two electrons each one
has its spin
and they're very very far apart they
don't interact with each other there's
no energy associated with the
interaction between them but as you
bring them together there are all sorts
of energies one energy for example is
just a Kum energy between them product
of the charges there is also an energy
associated with the spins and one of the
terms in the energy associated with the
spin is just the dotproduct of the spins
if the spins are aligned you get if if
this is aligned you get one value if
they're anti-aligned you get the other
value and so sigma.
to is a piece of the
hamiltonian of uh of the two spin
system in the singlet State it's
minimum there's three other states
called the triplet state in which it's
maximum so the energy is lowest in the
singlet State this this spins are trying
to get anti anti-aligned with each other
but in every direction not just the Z
Direction in every direction and they
eventually compromise on the singlet
state so you have two energy levels
associated with the spin of an electron
these two energy uh in hydrogen or in
patronum even better in positronium you
have the aligned and anti-align Spins
and they have different energy levels
singlet triplet
if you bring two electrons together then
any state can be written in terms of the
singlet and triplet States even the
product State can be represented as a
sum of singlet and triplet States what
happens when you bring the electrons
together after a period if they're in
the triplet state with a higher
energy what happens to higher energy
states after a
while they emit a Photon and go to the
lower energy state so if you take two
spins which may be in a product State
and you bring them together and wait a
long time a photon may or may not be
emitted if the system is in the singlet
State no emission if it's in the triplet
state it emits gives off a photon and
winds up in the singlet state so this
would be a way of preparing the system
in a singlet State you just take the two
electrons and wait until until they
radiate a photon wait long enough they
either do or don't radiate the photon
but if you wait long enough you'll know
that it's in the singlet
State all right so that's uh that's a
experiment that's an experiment to
another way another way now this one's
uh this one is um very very far-fetched
extremely far-fetched
the energy in the singlet state is less
than the energy in the other three
states there are four uh four Poss
possible States altogether four possible
basis States singlet and three triplet
the energy of the singlet is
lowest so you just take your composite
system and you put it on a scale and you
measure its mass mass is energy when
you've measured its mass you've measured
whether its energy is the energy of the
singlet State or the triplet State and
that constitutes a
measurement or constitutes a preparation
device or a measurement
of basically this variable but if you
like the difference between singlet and
triplet so yeah there are ways of
preparing systems in a singlet or
triplet in the singlet state or ways of
uh in fact if you bring the systems
together and you wait a while it's very
difficult to have anything but the
singlet State then once you've made that
singlet state if you grab the electrons
without turning the spins if you grab
them some in a way that doesn't put any
torque on their spins and pull them
apart you now have two separated
electrons for example in the singlet
state so it's it's not a terribly hard
thing to
do this me that you can actually assign
energy to the entanglement yes in this
case yes in this in this case yes but
the but that's
well what you can say is the lower
energy is certainly entangled the lowest
energy State the one that it seeks when
it uh to get to by and it doesn't have
to be radiating a photon any mechanism
by which the system can lower its energy
um em emitting a phonon or doing
interacting with a crystal lattice or
anything to lower its energy will leave
it in the singlet state
so and I think the right thing just to
say is that the uh that the lower energy
state is entangled that's almost always
the
case uh that um that the states of
lowest energy are highly entangled
between
systems okay so
we next question is there a measure is
there a quantitative measure of the
degree of
entanglement is there a way of taking a
state and
determining whether it's entangled and
to measure how much it's
entangled okay that brings us to a
concept called the density Matrix which
I'm probably going to it's getting later
than I thought so I want to um I want
to go over this a little quickly but I
think we can uh we can do
it let's define an object called Alice's
density Matrix
Alice's density
Matrix is a quantity which even in an
entangled state is as complete a
description of Alice's system for the
purposes of Alice's measurements as
Alice can ever
get it's not a wave
function if it was unentangled the wave
function would be the best description
she could have but for an entangled
system you cannot extract out a wave
function for either piece of the
entangled system the best you can do is
something called the uh the density
Matrix we actually had it up here let me
go back to
it let's talk about all of Alice's
experiments that she can do without
measuring anything about Bob's electron
or Bob's system let's imagine that
they've separated their systems Bob has
his Alice has her and Alice can do all
the experiments she likes and measure
any one of these l
observables L stands L standing for
Alice okay uh how does she describe all
the possible expectation values of
everything that she can ever measure so
we had a formula up before and I'm going
to rewrite it expectation value of L is
SAR
of
alpha let's see what was it Alpha
Prime beta prime or a a prime B Prime
this is the combined system we're going
back to the combined system now
um l a prime
a s a b but we set uh we set b equal to
B
prime or if we like we can leave the B
Prime here and put a chronica Delta of B
and B
Prime this is one of Alice's
variables and so as far as Bob goes it's
just the unit operator does nothing to
Bob's piece of the wave function and
that just says stick b equal to B
Prime okay look at this quantity right
over here let's take L on the outside
let's take L of a prime and a out there
isolate it off we have to sum this over
B we sum over everything we sum this
over B and here's a quantity
right here that depends on a prime a and
it multiplies something else that
depends on a and a prime but it doesn't
depend on B we've summed over B once
you've summed over B it doesn't depend
on B
anymore so this object over here is a
function only of Alice's coordinates a
and a
prime it of course to calculate it you
may have to know more the wave function
but once you've calculated it that's all
that Alice ever needs to know to
calculate anything about her half of the
system so let's give it a name it's the
sum over
B
siar of A Prime b s of a b it doesn't
depend on the B degrees of freedom at
all anymore Bob's degrees of freedom
it's called the density Matrix and it's
a function it's a thing which depends on
a prime and a it's a matrix it's a
matrix it has two entries any Matrix can
be thought of as a
function of a row and a
column this is a density Matrix and if
we know the density Matrix doesn't
matter where it came from doesn't matter
what Bob state was if we know row row
then we know that the expectational let
write the formula the expectation value
of L is equal to the sum of row of a
prime and a l of a and a prime I think I
have one of them backwards it doesn't
matter so Alice if she knew this density
Matrix could forget about Bob completely
and say I know everything that there is
to know about my
subsystem and here it
is okay
what is row of a and a
prime if we start with a pure
State supposing we started with a pure
state are you getting
exhausted well this is quantum mechanics
for you sorry buddies but this is
it I can't I can't make it any easier
this is as easy as I can make it all
right you got to sit down with it and
you got to go through it and uh and
penetrate it but uh I'll do my
best okay this is the notion of a
density
Matrix what
if
s is a pure State what can we say about
this density Matrix so let's go back and
see exactly what it says if sign is
sorry what if SII is a product state if
s is a product state it means the wave
function factorizes so let's go back
here we are here's the density Matrix
the wave function factorizes into a this
is B Prime yeah that's right that's
that's correct density Matrix your Su is
over a and a a not in the not in the
density Matrix in this one yes it's a
double sum it's a double sum but it only
involves rows so let's erase this for a
moment and see what we learn about this
creature called the density Matrix if s
is a product Vector it must have a a
special form somehow so let's say that s
is a product of Alice's wave
function times Bob's wave function I
forget which one is which now wasai
Alice or wasai
Bob s was
Bob s is Alice okay it doesn't matter we
change them now
so the the uh the complex conjugate here
is Alice's wave function times this is
not the wave function of Alice this is
the wave function of Alice's spin
incidentally but I'll call it Alice's
wave function Alice's wave function
times Bob's wave function the complex
conjugate and then we multiply that
by the non-c complex conjugated thing
let me put them in the opposite order F
of B notice we've identified B with B
here it's not B and B Prime
and this is prime S
A each one of these factorizes this
factorizes into a function of a prime
and B and this one into a function of b
and
a and now we sum over a
b what is the sum of B of five star five
one
right okay so now we can take this out
and throw it
out and here's what we find we find that
for a product state only for product
state that row is simply made up out of
Alice's half of the wave function
without any regard to Bob she doesn't
need to know anything about
Bob this is not too surprising that she
didn't need to know anything about
Bob after all it is a product wave
function and the density Matrix is just
a
um
a product of the complex conjugate of
the wave function with the wave function
itself two different A's though an A and
an a
prime now what can we say about
a matrix like this let's call this
Matrix let's call it I think it's
actually row of let's call it row of a
and a prime
just call it row of a I I've switched
the order but that's just a
definition let's take this row it's a
matrix and act with it on a column
Vector how do you act if you know the
components of a matrix how do you act on
a column Vector so let's suppose this is
a
matrix here excuse me yeah Row one one
just a second row one two so forth Row 2
one we make a matrix out of it yeah do
you want to erase that sign there on the
far yeah I
do good
point
excellent all right so we have row it's
made up out of Alice's wave
function and I
maintain that this density Matrix
thought of as a matrix has an igen
Vector I maintain moreover that it has
one and only one igen vector with
nonzero igen value and that that igen
value is +
one somebody say right
good okay let's prove it I'll tell you
exactly what that I Vector is it's sa a
it's Sai itself it's s itself so let's
check that out let's multiply this by S
of a prime in fact and sum it over a
prime this is Matrix this is the process
of multiplying a column vector by a
matrix that's the way you do it you
write down the Matrix you write down the
column vector and you sum over the uh
the element uh between
them okay let's see if we can see what
we
get oh this is the action of row on
S okay so let's do it
row is
row now let's multiply it by S of a
prime and now let's sum over a prime
what do we
get S star of a prime * s of a prime Su
a prime is one right so it all comes out
to just be
S so this is s
what does that tell you about igen
vectors and igen values of the density
Matrix it tells you that the original
wave function is an igen Vector of the
density Matrix with igen value +
one let me prove now that all vectors
perpendicular there are n minus one if
the dimensionality of the space is n
then this is one igen vector out of n
which has igen value one
let's take any Vector now which is
perpendicular which is
orthogonal to S to S A to Alice's wave
function let's call it sa a tilder
tilder now means it's orthogonal to the
original Alice's
Vector now what is this inner
product zero
right so we find out that row
on side twiddle is
zero that means that any Vector
perpendicular to Alice's
Vector is an igen Vector with igen value
zero the
original state of alysis spin is an igen
Vector with plus
one conclusion the density Matrix for a
pure state has one and only one nonzero
igen value and it's equal to one
what if it's not a product
state if it's not a product
State then you find a a collection of
igen values in fact in general there
will be all of the igen values in
general will be nonone zero of the
density Matrix you can try this out for
the
um uh for the two spin system work out
the density Matrix of
Alice's spin the density Matrix for
Bob's Spin and you will find out that
they're quite different they don't have
a single igen Vector which is nonzero
they have a pair of igen vectors which
are
nonzero so what we what we learn is that
there's information in the density
Matrix and in particular in the igen
values of the density Matrix which tell
you whether there's a great deal of
entanglement or not the more igen
vectors which are nonzero the more
entangled it is if there's only one igen
vector which is
nonzero it's not entangled at all
and Alice's half of the wave function is
just that igen
Vector if they're entangled then one
finds and and the more they're entangled
the more igen values you will
find and the maximum entanglement is
when all the vectors are equal when all
the igen vectors are equal all igen
values when all the igen values are
equal that's maximal
entanglement
take the singlet State work out the
density Matrix of Alice's Spin and what
you'll find is that it has two igen
values each of which is a half equal and
equal to a
half so that's a test that's the way to
test whether a system does or doesn't
have entanglement calculate its density
Matrix and study its igen values the
maximal entanglement is when they're all
equal when they're equal they're equal
to 1 /
n you can prove that where n is the
dimensionality of the space one /
n okay that's uh that's entanglement
Quantified
can even be a little more
quantitative even be a little more
quantitative no let's not do that now I
I'll I'll write the more quantitative
condition in notes and uh I think we've
done enough uh enough
um calculation for the moment
let's very quickly go through the
connection between measurement and
entanglement there's a deep connection
between measurement and
entanglement basically measurement is
the process of entangling of starting
with a product State a product state of
what and what a product state of a
system and the
apparatus the apparatus is in a definite
state to begin with and the system is in
a definite State what state is the
apparatus in well well the apparatus
might be something which detects
something or other and if it's not
detecting you might put it in some
neutral State some neutral state which
is the starting State the undetected uh
State neutral state of the apparatus and
now you bring the system that you're
interested in right up to the apparatus
it does something to the apparatus
something happens to the system itself
and what's left over is an entangled
State between the two of them so I'll
give you an example I'm going to think
of the apparatus is a very simple system
with only two
states Let's uh let me find my notes
Here
Yeah Yeah my system is a spin and my
apparatus also happens to have only two
states you can think of it as another
spin if you like in fact it could be
Alice's and Bob's but you can also think
of it as a more complex
system but for Simplicity it only has
two
states here's the
apparatus and has only two states plus
uh let's say zero and one now zero is
the state before the apparatus is
switched on well when it's switched on
when it's switched on and it's not
detected anything it always starts out
in the state zero if it's not in the
state zero give it a sharp and make it
uh put it into the state zero otherwise
it's not uh
otherwise uh you know you have to start
your apparatus in some known State
otherwise you're not going to be able to
do a measurement so it has Zer or one
but it starts out zero and we have our
spin here's a spin and we're going to do
a measurement on
it supposing the spin is in the
upstate and the apparatus of course
begins in the zero state so we'll
represent that by a combined K Vector a
combined K Vector is in the tensor
product of the spin Hilbert space and
the detector Hilbert
space up and
zero if the spin comes in to begin with
down then you start out in the space in
the state down
zero why because you start out with a
detector in the neutral
State now I'm not going to tell you in
detail what the interaction is between
the detector in the uh in the spin that
could involve magnetic fields and other
kinds of things uh causing an influence
between the detector but I am going to
tell you that if you bring the spin into
the detector and then take the spin out
of the detector I will tell you what
state is left over so in particular
and I'm making this up of course I'm
making up a rule which would be a good
detector which would be a good detector
namely if the spin if the system starts
if the combined system starts in the
state
u0
then the detector feels a spin and it
jumps to State one it goes to State U1
nothing happens to the
spin it just activates the
detector on the other hand if the spin
is down it doesn't activate the detector
that's my rule so this goes to down
one no down zero down
zero and that's a very good detector of
upness and
down but now let's start with a
superposition of up and down let's
take Alpha up time
up plus Alpha
down times down somebody now brought us
a spin in a superposition of stat in a
general Quantum state but of course the
detector starts out
zero so that's the starting
State what happens after the detector
Acts
well if the state is Al is u0 it goes to
U1 so that means it goes to Alpha sub
U time
U1 plus Alpha
subd down
zero this all of a sudden has become an
entangled State it's an entangled state
if it's up if the spin is up the
detector is up the detector is one if
the spin is down the detector is zero
that is an entangled State why is it an
entangled State it's an entangled State
because by looking at the detector you
can tell what the spin is doing in fact
that's what a measurement is a
measurement is an interaction between a
system and an apparatus that leaves the
apparatus in a
state that that depends on the whatever
it is that it's measuring about the
system so from one point of view you can
just say well look this is exactly what
I knew a measurement always
was it just is a Le it's just a process
that leaves a record on the apparatus of
what the initial state was of the of the
spin but from another point of view it's
the physics of a combined system the
combined system being the Spin and the
apparatus which leaves them in a highly
entangled state so entangled that by
looking at the detector you can tell
what the spin
is so entanglement and measurement are
really the same
thing and in fact to measure a spin you
really only need another
spin uh this uh the detector here could
just be a spin and one and zero could be
up and down so if we had this kind of
concoction here where exactly this
happened it would take only one spin to
be a detector or an apparatus which
could measure another spin but in
general um this is the nature
of measurement that it entangles systems
together it entangles in particular
apparatus with
system um
is that
clear should be very clear and that's
all that's that's one way of thinking
about measurement in this language in
which you think of the system and the
apparatus together you never speak about
collapse of the wave function you speak
about the development of entanglement if
you don't want to include the apparatus
into your system then the only thing to
say is that after the experiment is done
the system is either up or down and you
get and uh which one do you pick you
pick the one that you record but the one
that you record is the one recorded by
the apparatus so thinking about just the
system by itself you have to have this
rule that the wave function collapses
thinking about the system plus apparatus
the same physics is described by the
development of entanglement between the
system and apparatus
in that case for the for
the Bott what do you see on the meter of
your apparatus one
zero okay the app now you are another
detector right this is the hierarchy of
detection or the hierarchy of
measurement here's the
spin here's the apparatus but we're not
finished we still have to look at the uh
at the apparatus we haveen gotten
anywhere until we look at the apparatus
right all right well what's going to
happen again we're going to have to say
when we look at the apparatus we wind up
collapsing the wave function to one of
these two pieces of the entangled state
or we can say include the eyeball into
the system in that case we should have
included another system here the eyeball
and the eyeball I don't know how did it
start it started
uh
um
uh it also has two states the two states
correspond to the two possible answers
that the that the brain up there there's
also a brain up
here two states of the brain one state
of the brain says I
saw the apparatus with a zero the other
state of the brain says I saw the
apparatus with a
one if we want to include the Observer
as well as the apparatus we have to
include another Factor
here and that factor has to depend on
the state of the brain let's call it B
let's call it BAU it starts BAU which is
the Brain before it has looked at
anything and then it goes to B1 over
here or B not over
here it's now now become a system which
is entangled with the with the eye and
brain you can say wait a minute now we
now have this entangled State we've
described it all by the quantum
mechanics of the entanglement between
Spin and apparatus and then later on
between apparatus Spin and Eyeball it's
all been described by quantum
mechanics but you may not be satisfied
you may worry about the other fellow who
comes in in the room takes a look or
asks you what did you see so somebody
else comes
in and ask you okay Charlie what did you
measure and in the process
collapses the wave function of the um
spin apparatus what's his name give him
a
name no no no Charlie this is Charlie he
he comes in afterwards wigner Winer
wigner
Wiggy yeah this is wigner this is
Schrodinger right that's Wing So
Schrodinger and uh I don't know which
one of these has
ears this is the atom this is the atom
the cat he doesn't look at the atom but
he gets hit but something happen
something happens to him when the atom
so he's the
detector the cat is the
detector right here's schinger who looks
into the box and here's wigner who looks
at Schrodinger and there's a hierarchy
here the hierarchy where you decide to
break the hierarchy where you decide to
break the
hierarchy determines at what stage you
will say the wave function
collapsed if you like um
I suppose at some stage you have to say
the wave function
collapsed uh when the last person looked
at it but you could always include that
last person into the system and then no
collapse happens but then in order to
make sense out of the whole thing again
you have to imagine some other person so
you always have to imagine a hierarchy
of
observation uh and there is such a
hierarchy of observation the world is
built uh like a uh like an onion uh
things inside next thing out next thing
out next thing out and each thing gets
to observe what's uh in the inside of
it question what is the
process whereby we move into the
classical world and one of those people
actually see the definite
value well I don't
know um
I don't think there is any sharp line I
I don't think there is any sharp line we
tend to describe big
systems
uh as having little
uncertainty but
um I'm not sure that anything really
different
happens when uh when a electron looks at
another electron or when a cat looks at
an electron I think the physics or the
mathematical description I think is the
same
description or at least uh if we want to
say something special happened when the
cat looked that's not well described by
quantum mechanics we have to introduce
something about cats uh that uh isn't
contained within quantum mechanics and
personally I don't believe there is
anything about cats which is not
contained within quantum mechanics so
I'm happy with this description I'm
happy with this description
what makes me happy is that it doesn't
matter where you draw the line you can
draw the line in one place or the next
place or the next place and the results
will be
consistent if the can't s the spin up
Schrodinger will see the cat having seen
the spin up and wigo will have seen
Schrodinger having seen the cat having
seen the spin up that's what the nature
of the state is so that that I find
satisfying that you don't ever have to
say where you draw the line and until
you draw the line you can put the line
as far out as you like until you draw
the line everything is described by the
rules of uh conventional quantum
mechanics um so like you're the cat you
definitely drawn the line well okay yeah
I
mean yeah um look I think at some stage
you have to decide for yourself how you
think about this I'm not going to try to
push my
interpretation of quantum mechanics on
you um
particularly
since uh I don't know what to say about
it except
this uh this seems to disturb a lot of
people this whole business of
systems which for which you can know as
much as can be known and know nothing
about the parts of the system it seems
to disturb
people uh is it
disturbing I'm you know when Fineman was
asked whether he thought there was a
problem about quantum mechanics his
answer was the problem is so big that he
couldn't tell if there was a problem he
knew how to use it he knew how to
predict with it he could predict
anything that he wanted to predict uh
that had a that had an answer and uh he
did not expect I'm qu I'm actually
speaking about myself now but uh he and
for him he did not expect that quantum
mechanics would ever go wrong that the
rules would always be
satisfied but is there a problem because
of this sense of unreality about where
actual objective where objectively does
something happen does the
objective death of the cat happen when
the cat looks at the atom or is it when
Schrodinger looks at the cat or was it
is it when wigner looks at schinger
where does the objective phenomenon
happen and maybe we're just um playing
with words there maybe we're playing
with words trying to use words in a
context where they don't apply but you
have to decide that yourself my goal is
to give you the tools to be able to ask
the question and uh I doubt seriously
that you're going to answer the question
even for yourself you'll probably come
away feeling as uncomfortable uh about
it but you'll know why you're
uncomfortable you'll know what it is
with some Precision that's making you
uncomfortable about it at least I hope
at least that's uh my
goal all right
um in the equation you put up there with
the the ey forget
about just the ey the equation you wrote
that implies there's a correlation of
one between the state of the system the
apparatus the composite State and the
state of the eye the eye yeah so would
it in other words the eye has become
entangled with the rest of the system
now suppose your vision wasn't so
good that is what you call a weak
measurement yeah look no no that can
happen there can be partial there can be
partial entanglement for sure I've given
you a kind of idealized situation right
no no right question no it's a serious
question people uh people talk so good
you're not quite sure what the apparatus
is say well your I no no okay there
could be several reasons why your eye
was no good first of all it could be
that the interaction with the apparatus
was simply too weak that there wasn't
enough oomph in the interaction it
wasn't that your eye was bad it just
wasn't enough coupling between the two
systems and then you only get partial
information or it could be that your eye
is bad because you have cataracts let's
say all right in that case the eye did a
measurement it became entangled with the
uh with the system
completely it's just the connection
between
the uh the stuff in your eye and your
brain wasn't uh good enough to send the
signal back to your brain so so the
correlation happened uh but uh it was a
bit it was a bit messy is that a
detector efficiency problem that uh
sometimes it's a detector efficiency
problem and sometimes it's a
problem well detector efficiency could
have to do with the strength of
interaction with a system or it could
just be that it's too hard to get the
signal out so I'm not sure what detector
efficiency really means but I could
think of several things one is the
signal is there it imprinted itself on
the system and you personally have a
hard time getting it out the other is
that the interaction was not strong
enough to really establish a full
entanglement between these systems both
can happen how about a lip reader
watching a dub movie
right so would it affect L detector you
can think of all sorts of variance on
this would you would it affect a l
detector sir let's say there was a bad
detector in between that got entangled
and then I had a perfectly good detector
later on would it affect the measurement
of that well I think this probably I
guess the weakest link is where you uh
yeah all right let's talk about locality
let's talk about let's talk about
locality and entanglement which is
really where people get hung up I mean
and the villain the arch villain
here
who really Tangled things
badly was
Einstein Einstein and not that he asked
a question of course he asked a
wonderful question about entangled
systems really our understanding of
entanglement and much of what we think
about it and our curiosity about it goes
back to Einstein's question in
1933 uh who was very much puzzled by
this idea that you could have a system
about which you knew everything and yet
you knew nothing about the components of
it and uh he wrote a paper simply
complaining about it I don't know if he
was the first one to notice the
phenomenon of entanglement I have a
feeling not he was the first one to
get really exercised by it and say
something is very peculiar here that
that I find uh quite okay he then used
the term uh what what was the term again
um spooky action at a
distance and that got everybody confused
afterwards because Einstein knew exactly
what action at a distance meant and it
didn't
mean what he meant when he was using it
in this context action at a distance
literally means forces between systems
at a distance the ability to affect the
outcome of an experiment at one place by
doing something at another place action
at a distance um the Kum force between
electrons now of course in in the real
world it's not action at a distance but
in Newton's World well Newton didn't
know about electrons Newton knew about
the gravity in Newton's world the
gravitational interaction was action at
a distance and the meaning of that from
our point of view is that if something
came along and gave the the uh the Sun a
sudden shove we would know it instantly
for the simple reason that uh that the
orbit of the of the Earth would
instantly react to the change in
position of the sun the force on the
Earth would inst stly react and so every
measurement of everything that you might
want to measure would be to some extent
or another
Modified by the sudden uh the sudden
change in the orbit of the sun that's
what action at a distance meant the
ability if you like to send a signal by
shoving the sun you're sending a signal
to Earth and you're sending it
instantaneously if there's action at a
distance Einstein must have known I am
certain that he knew that entanglement
did not entail action at a distance in
that
sense
um what one can do what one can work
out is supposing you start I'll give you
something you can try to play with and
see if you can work it out supposing you
start with a system which is a two-part
system it has a wave function s of A and
B and from that system you can construct
a density mat here Alice and Bob you can
construct a density Matrix Row for
Alice that density Matrix contains every
possible or
um statistical prediction that Alice can
ever make for her subsystem a now let's
imagine that Alice and Bob took their
subsystems Alice went uh to a distant
planet Bob stayed in
paloalto and they're very far from one
another so far that it would take light
four years to get from one place to
another Bob does an
experiment that means now this is this
is an entang this could be an entangled
State this is not a non-entangled state
Bob does an
experiment and that has an effect on his
half of the system here but it has no
effect whatever on Alice's density
Matrix perhaps I can prove that I'm not
going to prove that tonight it uh it's
not too hard to prove that
any physically
allowable change in this wave function
which only involves Bob half of it the
process of interacting with some other
system or whatever it is Bob gives his
electron a knock whatever he does to it
he will not have any effect on Alice's
density Matrix that's the way quantum
mechanics is really put together and the
implication is that anything that Bob
does Suddenly at a fixed instant of time
will not have any effect on any
prediction or any or the success of any
prediction it will have no effect on the
statistical probabilities of Alice
measuring anything about a it just will
not uh
um so in that sense it was impossible
for Bob to send a message to Alice
suddenly now of course he can do an
experiment on his
subsystem and after he's done the
experiment he can then send a telegram
to Alice far away in the standard way
that you send messages and tell her what
there is so again uh this is an
entangled state it could be up down
minine is down
up when Al when Bob does a measurement
on his spin it has no effect on Alice's
density Matrix he can then send Alice a
message and say look I saw down and
Alice will say ah yeah that's because I
saw
up they were correlated I thought they
were correlated and you just confirmed
that I measured up few few months ago
and in fact I'm now getting you Telegram
and it tells me that you got
down and uh that's consistent everything
is fine nobody sent any message faster
than the speed of light the mere fact
that
when uh Bob measures his variable he
instantly knows something about Alice's
is no no source of anxiety for uh for
locality this would happen for for
nickels and dimes if for perfectly
classical systems the peculiarity is
different than that the peculiarity has
to do with this idea that you can know
everything about a system and yet know
nothing about its
parts
um what what is it then if this locality
the standard physicist definition of
locality is not at
risk and uh you can't send signals
faster what is it that Einstein meant
and what did Bell mean and what did all
the other people who talk about these
things mean when they
said entanglement entails a degree of
nonlocality so I'll try to explain to
you by imagining a
game yeah if Bob made a measurement and
Alice did not and Bob sent Alice a
message after his measurement would that
information alone be enough to change
Alice's density IND be enough to what to
change Alice's density Matrix oh yeah if
Alice sends a real if Bob sends a real
message and Alice hasn't looked yet okay
so let's
say Bob Alice has not looked she doesn't
know anything yet and as far as she's
concerned the density Matrix is
consistent with that and basically tells
her nothing that's a density Matrix
which hasn't got very much information
in it about her Spin and then she gets a
telegram from Bob saying my spin was up
as far as Alice is concerned that
collapses her density Matrix and tells
her her spin is down so if thereafter
she will use a density Matrix which says
that her spin is down so yes once a
message has had time to go between them
yes then she will uh she will know
something that she didn't know
before and she will therefore update her
density Matrix but that will only take
place after uh after there's been
sufficient time to uh for the signal to
propagate yeah um if I understand
correctly the statements that we're
making here are about expected values of
of of these experments right yes but
when you realize it once you're actually
not going to get the expected value
you're going to get but this also holds
for every value not just expected values
right uh no expected or expectation Valu
or whatever you want to call them
average values if you know the average
values of all variables you don't need
to know let's okay supposing we have one
variable that we're interested in let's
call it l again if we know the average
value of
L the average value of L squared the
average value of L cubed dot dot dot we
know the whole probability distribution
of L this is called knowing the moments
all of the moments of a probability
distribution if we know all the
expectation values of l l s l
cubed actually for a single spin you
only need the spin and the spin
squared uh then you know the full
probability distribution once you know
the full probability distribution that's
all you can
know so um so knowing all knowing a full
set of expectation values like this is
knowing everything that Alice can know
about the system
realiz expent oh that that's right yes
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah that's that's
right they are they guaranteed to be
opposite yes I guess but Alice cannot
find Alice doesn't update her
information about it until she gets
before Alice gets the information as far
as she knows it's half a half but let's
let's try to do a little better Al Alice
and Bob are now going to each have Min
spins right so Charlie is going to give
each of them many entangled
pairs so Alice has spin number one and
Bob has his spin number one and they are
in the uh relationship of being
entangled also Alice has spin number two
which is not entangled with spin number
one but happens to be entangled with
Bob's spin number
two Charlie gave him a whole series of
these so that they can do statistical
experiments and collect
statistics
um when they've collected statistics
they will discover that every time uh
Bob is up Alice is down every time Bob
is down Alice is up but now they can do
a lot more than that they can um let's
see what's a what's a good example for
what uh can be
done
um yeah right good Bob does all of his
experiments here at some instant of time
and finds out every one of these finds
out exactly what every one of them is
doing does that convey any information
at all to Alice about which which she
knows that just about half of them are
up and half of them are
down Bob goes and makes his measurement
he does his measurement on every single
one of them does Alice know anything
afterward that she didn't know before no
does anything surprising happen when she
measures these things does the
statistics of these things over here in
any way change because Bob measured
these things no there will be no
statistical difference
Bob can do his
measurement throw his measurement in the
waste paper basket but he's measured
every single one of these it has no
influence at all on what Alice
measures but if Bob sends a message to
Alice before she does her measurement
and says spin one came out plus spin two
came out minus blah blah blah then
instantly Alice knows everything about
these in fact he could say Sigma Z
equals + one but he decided over here
not to measure Sigma Z he said I'm going
to measure Sigma X over here minus one
and over here he measures Sigma y =
+1 having made these
measurements without informing Alice in
any way does nothing whatever to the
statistics of her measurements but if he
now sends
them she can now decide she can decide
to measure anything she wants but but if
she decides to measure Sigma Z because
she knew that Bob got plus one here and
sigma X for this one and sigma y for
this one we'll find that in every case
that they're opposite you keep saying um
Bob sends the message I just want to
make sure I understand yeah that's
telegram it's not him sending it it's
her receiving it that matters well of
course yes right no the important point
is that it takes time to send a message
yeah h
what I missed
okay well yes that is a
problem I don't know if the caption it
seems like this feeling about spooky
action at a distance comes not from
thinking externally about Bob and Alice
doing measurements but almost thinking
about inside the system like there are
these two separate entities
well I will try to give you a precise
definition all right now I there is a
theorem lurking here I don't know that
the theorem has ever been discussed in
the computer science Community it's a
it's a kind of computer science theorem
um whether anybody has actually
discussed it in the language I'm going
to tell you now I don't know and I don't
really quite know how to formulate it as
a as a theorem I've never tried um but I
think I can capture the essence of what
the of what this theorem would say if
only the theorem could be made
precise all we have 10 minutes to try to
do this if we go over a little bit uh
we'll have to we'll do
that here's the game I want to
play I want I'm going to write a
computer program my computer my computer
has a screen okay it has a screen and
all the usual things that computers have
over here on the screen is a little
black box and that little black box is
called
spin you can't see inside it but there's
something in it and in here is apparatus
a and apparatus a you can see you can
see what what it's doing and so forth
right it's got a zero it can measure
zero or one now here's the game um the
memory stores two things the memory
stores information about the spin this
is a completely classical computer the
game going to play is I'm going to fool
you into thinking there's really a
quantum mechanical system in here how
are we going to do that we're going to
do it by I'm going to write a computer
program which completely simulates the
classical computer program that
completely simulates what happens when
an apparatus looks at a at a
spin okay so here's the way it's going
to go
um we're going to start just uh just for
convenience we'll start with a spin in a
known state right so the apparatus or or
the computer
program it's not important but the
computer program let's say it starts out
with the spin up or whatever it's
doing the
apparatus can either read zero or
one there's a button over here in this
there's a button there's a button over
here that you touch and that button is
m means you measure means measurement so
when you touch that button over here the
apparatus measures the
spin the computer records two things it
records the state Vector of the spin how
does it do that by providing two complex
numbers stored in the computer are two
complex numbers Alpha up and Alpha down
subject to the constraint that Alpha
star Alpha plus Alpha star Alpha is
equal to
1 so it stores a information which is
equivalent to the state Vector of the
spin and the other thing it stores is
the direction that you point the
apparatus you can move the apparatus
around by playing with a computer not
move it around but you can reorient it
in any direction that you
like you start with a spin up now this
spin might be interacting with a
magnetic field or whatever's happening
to it the computer solves the
Schrodinger equation and solving the
rotinger equation for the spin that
means it updates the state of the spin
you start with a particular State
doesn't matter what it is and after a
Time T it updates the spin the it
updates the state so the computer now
knows what Alpha is after a certain time
has
elapsed then you punch the measure
button and the
computer takes the state turns it into a
pair of probabilities Alpha star Al Al
up Alpha star Alpha down the computer
now knows the probability for up and
down and it also has a random number
generator random number generators are a
dime a dozen and they work very well
with a random number generator it then
takes the probabilities Alpha up and
Alpha down and spits out a number plus
or minus one with
probability Alpha star Alpha and Alpha
star Alpha so it just simulates the
quantum mechanics by having a random
number
generator that either spits
out plus one or minus one but with a
probability that's given by Alpha star
Alpha all right but then the computer
then whatever the answer is whatever the
answer that the apparatus spit out the
computer then updates once again the
state of the spin and says it is in the
state that the apparatus measured so if
the apparatus spits out plus one along
some axis the you you get to turn the
apparatus but
uh because when you get to turn the
apparatus you have to do a slightly
complicated calculation to find out what
the what the statistics are but once
you've done it whatever the answer is
the computer goes back and updates the
state of the spin to make it consistent
with what the apparatus measured you can
do this
you can try to write a program this a
program that uh that could be written
it's probably not even terribly
complicated and if you were only got to
look at the measuring button decide to
measure and look at the outcome you
would get everything exactly equivalent
to the extent that a random number
generator can be a good faithful random
number generator you would completely
simulate the quantum mechanics of the
system the lesson is that quantum
mechanics can be a special case of
classical physics so what's going on
what the if quantum mechanics can be a
special case of classical mechanics
what's all this
um uh confusion about quantum mechanics
being logically different all right now
we want to play the same game with a
pair of
spins question you said that qu you're
trying to say quantum mechanics is a um
a special case of classical but I
thought in classical everything was
deterministic but introducing the
probability okay but it's on yeah yeah
yeah but it's own this is a classical
computer and it's using a classical
number generator a classical random
number generator right so you do have to
add in a but the difference between
quantum mechanics and classical
mechanics isn't Randomness you can
generate all sorts of random number
generators that would easily fool you
into thinking they were really random
course any real random number generator
the numbers come from somewhere so
they're not strictly random but uh you
can sure make a random number generator
that would fool
anybody so yeah you can you can build
you can build a computer program to
simulate the quantum mechanics basically
of any system that you like by the Same
by the same method okay but now
supposing you wanted to
simulate a system consisting of two
electrons there's two electrons two
boxes here and you wanted to do it with
two two
computers and in the process of taking
the electrons apart from each other so
as to ask this question about the you
want to take the computers you want to
encode the information about Alice's
spin in one computer and Bob's spin in
the other computer physically separate
them and ask can these computers
simulate quantum mechanics so I'll tell
you what the answer is as long as as the
um spins are in a product State as long
as they start in a product State and
they don't interact with each other and
therefore stay in a product State then
you can do it you can put all of the
information about Bob's spinning here
all the information about Alice's
spinning here likewise you can have
Bob's apparatus over here you can have
Alice's apparatus over here little black
boxes and it's just basic Bally two
identical uh versions of what I said
before you can take the computers
physically separate them do experiments
on each one and they will completely
agree with the results of quantum
mechanics because if they're in a
product State one doesn't care about the
other but then you say what if I wanted
to put these two spins in an entangled
State well first of all to put them in
an entangled State you cannot do it
without bringing the computerss together
bringing the computers together so that
they talk to each
other you can you can record in the
combined computer system now they
they're brought together how many uh how
many uh numbers does it take to to
specify the state of a uh two spin
system
six so you record six numbers in the
computer here
six numbers are recorded in the computer
and some numbers to reflect uh the
orientations of various uh of
various apparatuses that you might
conceive of and then you try to split
the computer into
two keeping Alice's information in here
and Bob's information in here separate
them and try to simulate the quantum
mechanics of the uh of the entire angled
system Bell's theorem is what tells you
that you cannot do this
unless there instantaneous action at a
distance phenomena taking place between
the a wires between the computer so to
speak hidden wires that have to be part
of the system connecting the computers
together you
canot
simulate the uh the quantum mechanics
with a classical computer system you
can't simulate the quantum
mechanics of an entangled system
unless it's really just one computer
really when one computer means that
signals can be transmitted back and
forth basically instantly that's what
Bells theorem really says now is this is
this a form of non-locality well you
might think that if to if if you really
have to have these wires there to
simulate quantum mechanics then why
can't you send an instantaneous message
through these wires of course you can
but not if you only allow yourself to do
the things which quantum mechanics
permits for example there are things
that quantum mechanics doesn't permit it
doesn't allow you to measure the X and Y
component of a spin
simultaneously all kinds of things that
it does not permit you to do because
they correspond to non-commuting
operators if you restrict yourself to
the measurements which quantum mechanics
allow allows you to do on either one of
these or any combination of them then
it's a very magical and special fact
that you cannot send information faster
than the speed of light you cannot send
information
instantaneously by this computer
setup what if you assign not
probabilities but conditional
probabilities doesn't matter doesn't
matter if you want to simulate a Quantum
system with a classical system of
computers and you want to study
entangled systems the computers have to
be able to communicate with each other
instantaneously that's that's the
content of Bell's
theorem now does that mean that there's
any action spooky action at a distance
or does it just mean that you've gotten
yourself into trouble by trying to
simulate quantum mechanics with
classical mechanics my view is that
you've gotten yourself into trouble by
trying to simulate something which just
doesn't want to be described by a
classical computer system and it's a
deep and interesting fact about quantum
mechanics Einstein's
view was that this is basically evidence
that uh that the description is
incomplete and that there are other
variables of the system and Bell's
conclusion was those other variables
have to be uh hidden wires that connect
distant
places
so you can
take it for however you see it yourself
yes so if you had a quantum computer
there and let's say when you had the
state you had a quantum computer you
could do it and you separated it right
now when you observe Bob's computer now
you know something about Alice is right
but you can't really still send no it's
the same problem right but look all a
quantum computer is is an electron in
this computer and an electron that's all
it is it's just a Quantum system right
it's just a true Quantum system a
Quantum system in each one of these
which has been entangled that's all a
quantum computer is it's a quantum
mechanical system which can reflect the
uh The Logical structures of quantum
mechanics and the way you make it is by
actually making a pair of entangled
electrons in there something real has
been entangled between them and it can't
be simulated by a fake computer program
unless the computer uh has this property
of uh but you still have the problem of
transmitting that information somehow oh
no you have sure sure
right um You you could sort of hack this
problem away if you using your analogy
we said that their pseudo random
generators were synchronized so there
are actually you know
notand
um Pro that you can do yeah yeah no but
what you can't do what you can't do is
synchronize them in
advance and then not let them interact
with each other that won't do it the
random numbers have to be random number
generators have to be such that what
this one measures responds to what that
one measured like like for example what
what I meant to say expl very well is
that the random number of generators are
are synchronized at the beginning and
whenever you measure they because
they're synchronized they will always
generate up and down reversed no they
lose the memory lose the memory ofly
State no it's simply it's simply not
enough this is what the theorem says it
is not enough to synchronize them in
advance and then take them apart they've
got to continue to interact with each
other that's what that's what it says
that they must continue to interact with
each other and feed information back and
forth
somebody the problem with the delayed
choice is if you put a filter in Bob's
instrument then
instantaneously Alice's correlation was
affected even if she is
years I told you everything I know about
it and what I know about it is that
there's nothing Bob can do which can
influence the statistics of Alice's
measurements without sending her a a
measure have to depend instantaneously
on the set of the dist
instrument
okay yeah
um one more minute one two more
questions forget action at a distance of
two separate computers I just find it
interesting that if you have a single
computer are you saying you can actually
classically
simulate uh quantum mechanics yes you
can classically simulate quantum
mechanics
but you basically have to do it within a
single computer where all parts of it
speak to every other part you cannot
physically take them apart the way you
would want to take the quantum systems
apart confused on being able to measure
the system of the versus the parts it
seems like you're measuring the parts of
the system Bob's making a measure of the
part Al is Mak a meas part I think one
of the statements you made was that you
the entire
no no an entangled system Bob can do his
measurements Alice can do her
measurements but there are other things
that can be measured besides just the
things that Alice would measure on her
system or the things that Bob would
measure for example neither Bob nor
Alice by themselves can
measure Sigma x * tox it takes both of
them to do it it takes both detectors it
takes both apparatuses to make a
measurement of Sigma x * tox this is
something that you cannot measure now
you can measure it with two apparatuses
the question is are there anything
things that you could measure that you
couldn't measure even with those two
apparatuses and yes there are Sigma X
tox plus Sigma y
toy plus Sigma Z to Z is something that
cannot even be measured by using both
apparatuses it takes a new kind of
apparatus which is not a combin
of Alice's and Bob's original
apparatuses which each measure a bob
thing and an ALICE
thing Bob cannot measure the
entanglement nobody can measure
entanglement you have to talk to there's
an
entanglement uh now Bob can discover
that he's got the if he has nobody can
do anything with one
event but if we have a whole replication
like I described over where where did I
describe it where we have many replicas
of the same
thing many replicas of the same thing
then Bob can discover the fact that his
state is entangled with something and
the way he does it is he says let me
search around for a direction in space
for which the spins are definitely
aligned in there some direction here's
what he knows he knows that all the
systems were prepared in the same way
they're all identical each pair is
identical to each other pair is
identical to each other pair and he's
wondering could each one of these be in
a product State same product state for
this one same product state for that one
same product state for that one if
they're in a product State then Bob can
search around he's got enough versions
of it enough uh trials that he can go on
and on with experiments
forever and he can search around for a
Direction Where when he measures the
spin his spin he always discovers that
it's up now the first time he he may be
in the wrong direction and he'll find
down next time he may find up he'll try
it again it'll be down wrong direction
and he keeps searching around if it's a
product State he will eventually find
the direction where the spin will
continue to be up up up up after he's
found it if it's an entangled State no
matter what direction he measures he
will will always find this uh the spins
are
random okay that's that's the character
of
it and that's on separate measurements
right on separate discrete measurements
not the measurement of the same thing no
you you've got to have an ensemble of
identical systems to do to do anything
like this you just prepare each one the
same way you do an experiment and he
doesn't care about Alice he's just going
to measure his spin along some axis
another axxis another axis until he
finds one where he keeps repetitively
getting the same answer and then he says
that's the direction that that spin is
polarized and then he keeps doing it and
finds consistency he'll never find that
unless it's a uh product state so it's
pretty pretty interesting
stuff hard
stuff for more please visit us at
stanford.edu